[Music]
yesterday we discussed the most
important theorem of this course which
was that when you count the intersection
number between two
subal you remember how to do this you
need orientation and you see whether at
each intersection the orientation joint
orientation is positive or negative with
respect to ambient orientation anyway
plus or minus one and then you add up
all those numbers and that's the
intersection number which can be
positive or
negative and then theorem
17 said that this intersection number
does not change when you deform the
picture that is the intersection number
is isotopy
invariant you remember
this and we show this by invoking a
picture again of pairwise creation
anation a little bit like when a
particle and anti particle came together
and poof disappear in a path of smoke or
out of vacuum boom and a pair of
positive and negative appear you cannot
create out of vacuum two positives
that's not possible
you cannot create out vacuum two
negatives but you can create one
positive and one negative that is
possible and also you can make one
positive and negative cancel each other
so to speak and disappear you cannot
cancel plus and plus or minus and minus
but positive and negative you can often
cancel okay today we shall
start with several applications of this
result so it follows from then that
Central theorem theorem
17 first of all an an obvious but very
um important result here 21 by now
that if you have two sarles
closed K and L can be disjoined by isop
in other words if you keep pulling them
farther and further apart and then they
get completely
[Applause]
disconnected then what happens after the
this jointed all together there's no
intersection well you know that the
intersection number is zero but that
means that to begin with the
intersection number had to be
zero okay so this joinability that's not
the proper English word but dis
joinability implies zero intersection
the converse is false in other words
even if the intersection number is zero
you may not be able to disjoin the two
subs here is an example to show that the
convice is
false
consider a reman surface of Genus 2
Sigma 2 and on
it we draw now a
curve as a manifold K which we shall
Orient in this
fashion this is reminiscent of the
picture that we saw yesterday but
yesterday we had a Taurus Sigma 1 and
then the curve was at the top but this
is slightly richer and then I'm going to
take another curve which goes around the
neck if you like and we shall call it l
and as usual the orientation on the
surface is what you expect E1 and E2 it
doesn't really matter what orientation
you take in fact E2
so let's see there are two intersections
here and here what is the intersection
number the sign here K goes this way L
goes this way so that's one two so
that's
positive and how about here that's K
goes this way L goes that way that's
negative of course
so the intersection
number of K and L is Zer because it's 1
+ 1 - 1 = 0
yeah
however however I change those I move
those curves on Sigma 2 I cannot disjoin
L from
K I can try to move L I can try to
deform K but there will always be
intersections you cannot get rid of
intersections
so we
cannot
disjoin K and
L by isotopy isotopy of course in you
have to say Sigma
2 if you go outside for example I can
think of L as made a rubber band and
then make this rubber band very large
and just take it out of the picture then
I can of course those but in order to do
so I have to go outside Sigma 2 and go
into for example R three ambient three
that's not
legal okay so we see that there's a
connection between disjoin ability and
zero intersection number but it goes
only in One Direction cor which is very
interesting Co stands for
cor I hope everyone can spell
this in
the ukan space
RM any to um closed sub
manifolds have intersection number
[Applause]
zero you should remember at this point
a challenge or problem that I gave you
yesterday and I think it was in ex
example 15 you remember I thought I
think it was here I drew a fair
complicated Loop another fairly
complicated Loop and we counted all
these signs and it turned out that the
intersection number was zero and we
asked whether it was possible to draw
two Loops inside
R2 such that the intersection number was
not zero and we say ected that it was
impossible we suspected that in R2 the
intersection number between two Loops
was always zero because there some sort
of alternation plusus plusus plus minus
do you remember
this this cor gives the solution to that
exercise in general in RM if you have
two close sub manifolds of course of
Dimension K and L such that they add up
to n otherwise intersection number
doesn't make sense they always have
inter section number zero and the proof
is very
simple I'm going to draw a picture in R2
but in general of course this picture is
the
same um let's note that we can move an
object in RM by just translating like
this okay just keep translating in One
Direction you might think translation
Works in any space but that's not true
for example here I canot keep
translating this L if I keep translating
I eventually get stuck so translation
works but only in some special spaces
but it works fortunately in RNs the
translation is an isotop of course so we
can use that Ty okay and what we shall
do that is that we
can translate
[Applause]
the
submanifolds in question are sub
manifolds so far away from each
other that they become
disjointed
that's once of my manifold for it k0
another sub
manifold l0 so they're intersecting in
many many points okay but grab this
curve and then pull it this
[Applause]
way let's call it K1 after I moved and
grab l0 pull it this
way and call it
L1 and after time one K1 and L1 are far
apart and there's no more
intersection therefore the intersection
number
is
zero so because the intersection number
is asolutely invariant in the beginning
without counting we can say that the
intersection number must be zero in this
picture okay and that's the proof that
the intersection numbers are always
zero
okay there are some other methods which
I shall of which I should mention one
instead of putting them apart you can
rescale for example let's take k0 and
make it smaller and smaller and smaller
and smaller and smaller and smaller okay
smaller and smaller but stop when while
it's still finite size but it's so small
that it becomes basically a point and
then you can sort of kick it so that it
doesn't intersect L Zer anymore and
that's an isotopy and in the final
configuration it's clear that there's no
intersection the intersection number
zero so it's the same
conclusion okay so the theorem 21
applies
good how how many of you have heard of
the Jordan curve
theorem Jordan curve theorem nobody
really William have you heard of Jordan
C theorem have you heard of the theorem
that if you
draw a loop in R2 that does not
intersect itself it divides the plane
into two regions inside and
outside who said yes please okay um
taboka
do you know what this theorum is called
yes what is it called the
Jordan
okay wait a minute 30 seconds ago I
asked have you heard of the Jordan C
theum and everyone said no and 30
seconds
later let me ask again have you heard of
the Jordan curve
theorem wow almost everyone says yes
what happened in the last 30
seconds I think what happened in the
last 30 seconds is that first you didn't
remember what Jordan car said and second
you all woke up okay good so many of us
have heard of Jordan C some of us may
not have but it's an obvious sounding
theorem which says that if you have a
curve a closed curve which does not
intersect
itself on the plane it divides the plane
into inside and outside you might say
it's not obvious I'll show you an
example
where it's not completely obvious okay
what shall we do we shall now not only
prove the Jordan car theem but prove a
vast generalization in any Dimension so
this
result the first big applied result that
we shall get in this course is the
generalization of the Jordan curb
theorem you might have heard also taboka
for example that the Jordan curb theorem
is is very difficult to prove you might
have heard this probably when you
encountered it in your undergraduate
studies the lecturer or the book said
it's true it's intuitive but it's very
difficult to prove so we will not prove
it now we shall prove it in a very easy
way thanks to
pictures the
statement in
RM so M can be anything not only two
RM every um closed closed means compact
without boundary as you remember hyper
surface what do we mean by hyper surface
I mean a surface or sub of Dimension
just one fewer than the ambient
Dimension so this is of
Dimension M minus one in the case of the
plane it is a curve in the case of the
usual three dimension
space it is a
Surface in general hyper surface when
this hyper surface is straight we call
it the hyper um plane as we know
separates the ambient RM into two
parts that's the statement when m equal
2 we have the classical Jordan C here
it is useful to begin by noticing
that although many textbook writers and
lectures say this is obvious it's not
obvious even in dimension
two consider the following picture
okay so I drew a
curve and it's a closed
[Applause]
curve okay is it really obvious to you
please be honest that this picture
defines two separate regions on the
plane I mean wouldn't you say you say
yes well how do you know that it doesn't
Define three separate plane separate
regions because I saw yeah exactly but
suppose that you saw this well even
after you saw me drawing I don't find it
obvious for example this point and this
point are they in the same part of the
and or not it's not clear at all right
so it's not obvious that the Jordan cve
theorem is true and moreover it's even
worse it's not obvious and in general
it's not even true so people who say
it's obvious are very much
[Applause]
misguided on General surfaces on General
spaces it is
not even true
for
example let's say that we are living not
on R2 but on T2 on the
Taurus two Dimension so the hyperface is
dimension 2 - one 1 it's a
curve on the Taurus you can draw a loop
which does not separate the Taurus to
Wi for example this curve it's a loop
but you see it does not separate the
ambient space into two
parts this point and this point are
connected you can go around in the
back so the theorem is by no means
obvious and in fact unless you state the
hypothesis correctly it's not even true
it's true because we are inside RM and
it turns out that it's also true on the
surface of a sphere in on SM in general
but otherwise it's not it's not true
okay
so we shall proceed now to the proof of
the generalized Jordan curve theorem
it's perhaps better called Jordan
surface theorem if you like let's argue
by contradiction so we shall assume that
the the conclusion is false in other
words that you have a closed
hypersurface which does not separate
suppose that such a situation is
possible and we shall arrive at
conclusion um contradiction so let's say
that this is K
hypersurface and it continues of course
because it's a Clos hypers surface I
don't know what it does it closes
somewhere goes somewhere and then closes
up okay
now let K be a
hypersurface that does not
separate
RM
okay we can take two
points very near K let's call them X and
Y yeah opposite each other across the
surface
K such that well because this surface
does not separate you can connect
X to
Y I don't know how but if you go
somewhere I can connect it back to Y for
example here I can connect this to this
in the back such a station okay so let's
draw a curve and then you know it does
something and then comes back and
connects it
to to Y in
words we can take
two
points X
Y
yeah
opposite each
other
across K you understand what I mean the
picture explains it
yeah such that X and Y
can be joined
by by a
curve let's call this curve gamma so
this is the beginning of gamma and then
this is also part of gamma curve
gamma that does
not cross SC
by the hypothesis of contradiction okay
now I shall close this
curve this curve is going all the way
around and coming back but let's add
this bridge between X and Y this bridge
crosses K of
course and the
bridge like
this between
X and
Y
okay
now
Bridge Union this
gamma if you go around gamma and then
the bridge it is a closed loop
okay so we have close two close sumar
fors one of them is K and the other one
is this whole Loop K is a hypersurface
so it has Dimension n minus one this
Loop has Dimension One n-1 + 1 exactly
the B Dimension M so these two can be
played with in the intersection Theory
but now you you see that if you look at
the intersection number of K
and this
bridge and and Gamma so this is the loop
and so on in how many points do they
intersect well at most one and I don't
know whether it's positive or negative
but it's plus or minus one and it's not
equal to zero which contradicts the
theorem that we have
before because in RM they always have
intersection number zero and the proof
contradicting which number was the
theorem cor excuse
me 23
apparently
okay that's how you can use the
intersection Theory to prove
results
okay in this proof I did not say
everything for example we Pro that such
a hypers surface TOS hypersurface must
separate RM I didn't say into two
parts okay but that's not too difficult
to prove it turns out um and I shall
omit the
details if you want to know about this
you can ask me but that's
um that's not all that important okay
are there any questions about what we
have done so far
this is the end of the current chapter
so I shall summarize in this chapter we
started introducing the theoretical
tools the main theoretical tools of our
subject that is the intersection number
before that we had to talk about
transversal intersections when
intersecting some manifolds have clean
if you like and robust stable generic
intersection sometimes the intersections
were very very ugly you know they were
tangent to each other and so forth but
we saw that the transversal
intersections were the general case and
if you had a transversal intersection it
was robust and peration if you changed
it a little bit it was still transversal
and conversely if you had a degenerate
non- transversal intersection then small
paration will make it transversal and we
defined the concept of intersection
number for transversal intersections and
show that this intersection number
theorem 17 from which we started was
isotopy invariant and the deformation of
pictures main approach to mathematics
and the deformation of pictures this
intersection number this new invariant
was
invariant
okay and we started using it in one
special case but that already gave us a
proof rather easy proof If you reread it
of what is supposed to be extremely
difficult prove the Jordan c z
okay
good let's then move on
to Applications of all this
material from now on we are halfway
through the course Wednesday of the
second week well congratulations on
Surviving so far
um from now on we have been climbing
climbing climbing and it to be descent
and will be harvesting lots and lots of
applications and I will try my best
within the limits of time to mention as
many applications to as diverse fields
of science as possible fields that
usually people do not think of as areas
of applications of topology and geometry
we shall also um consider those fields
so first topic is fix Point
theorems if you have been doing
mathematics for as long as you have you
have probably encountered fix Point
theorems and after the break today the
we shall begin a new sheet and it's all
about fixed Point theorems and you'll
see that there are lots and lots of very
cute problems that you can solve by
considering fixed
points here is the theoretical
discussion first why fixed Point
theorems what are they and why do we
care
motivation
suppose we need to
solve some
equation of the form G of xal
Z okay a very common station right one
can say that many people for many people
mathematics consist of solving equations
in fact it's such a widespread
misconception the people will say oh
equation mathematics equation equation
you equation this equation that when
there are lots of formulas in
mathematics that are not equations for
example this is not an equation it's
called an
inequality and still people insist on
calling it equation in fact you
[Music]
know this is not an equation it's an
it's a an equality equation means that
there's an
unknown and you have an equality and
from the equality you are trying to find
the unknown that's what's called an
equation okay so this is an equality
this is an inequality there are lots of
formulas in mathematics that are not
equations in fact most of the formulas
in mathematics are not equations but
equations are so important people think
that Ordinary
People not you because you are the great
educated Elite but uneducated people
will say oh mathematics equations
equations equations okay anyway
equations are important now this can
be this equation can be say
algebraic or discrete difference finite
difference did somebody sneeze in that
case bless you finite difference or
ordinary or partial differential
equations
[Applause]
integral equations if you like and so on
anything so consider any
equation x doesn't have to be a single
variable it could be multiple variables
multi variables it can be even an
infinite dimensional space anything so
any equation that you want to solve do
you agree that this is a very general
situation and if you can solve all such
problems we have made a lot of progress
you agree good in fact we can solve all
these
things let's
put Define a new function f ofx which is
simply equal to G of X Plus
X then
trivially G of X is zero if and only if
f ofx = x do you
agree but look this means that instead
of solving this equation you can find
points X that don't move or that are
fixed by F if you apply F it's the same
thing those are called fixed points let
you in fact to your loves twice at
this so
solving any
equation is
[Applause]
equivalent to
finding fixed
points set points about fixed points of
some
map it is just a translation but it
turns out to be a very powerful
translation so from now on we shall be
talking not about equations but every
time we have to deal with equations
we'll translate that
into this language by that simple trick
and talk about finding fixed
points okay so here
is a way to think about the
pictures the graph of G might look like
this okay and then the solutions of the
equation are here and
here you
agree what happens if I add the function
X to this graph well this is
X and the graph
gets rais a little bit that's going to
be the graph of
f okay this plus X you just shift it up
like that and to say that F ofx equal x
means that I'm looking at the
intersections of the graph of F and of
the graph if you like y = x so those two
points are the fixed points and you can
see it right because if I take a point
here look at its image it's exactly the
same value as before those are the
points that don't move is that clear so
we shall work with this picture which
captured the other picture